<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Power Plays]]></title><description><![CDATA[Exploring business models for energy distribution.]]></description><link>http://powerplays.io/</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2018 06:28:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Why energy matters to me]]></title><description><![CDATA[About four years ago, I started to understand why a poor person might choose not to drink clean water, or not to use a toilet. It wasn’t a…]]></description><link>http://powerplays.io//why-energy-matters/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://powerplays.io//why-energy-matters/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jun 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;About four years ago, I started to understand why a poor person might choose not to drink clean water, or not to use a toilet. It wasn’t a matter of education, or of access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was after I’d spent a few months touring different humanitech startups, going into rural areas in Ghana, Uganda, Tanzania. Meeting customers and non-customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember a lady explaining that the family’s budget goes towards saving for Typhoid meds, so auntie won’t die when it strikes again.  “To save money, we don’t buy drinking water.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was optimistic about all the solar-powered, mobile-phone on-gridding happening for the poor, but whenever I traveled a few kilometres outside of a major city, I’d see it made little difference. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next year, Matt at Standard Microgrid explained his practical view - if people can’t afford basic amenities like clean water and sanitation, the way to enable them is economically.  Solar-powered reading lights won’t do that, but enough amperage to use a sewing machine, a power tool or a fridge will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m excited that in our lifetime, we may see the end of extreme poverty.  At the same time, our ecological problems are clear.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way we currently distribute energy is ineffective. This is true whether you measure technical efficiency, or social equality. And underpinning both of these inefficiencies are the business models that drive energy companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These business models are changing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Energy distribution is such an exciting topic, and I’m starting to explore it - technically, economically, socially.  This blog is where I plan to share what I learn.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>